原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/xvltG-i6AS0
原视频发布日期：20201021
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
After months of searching
经过几个月的搜索
the crew on the International Space Station have finally located an elusive air leak in the Zvezda service module.
国际空间站上的乘员终于找到了那个藏在犄角旮旯里的漏气点 在星辰号服务舱中
And supposedly the crew technique for locating this tiny crack involved the innovative use of tea leaves
而据说乘员是通过巧用茶叶的方法才找到的这个微小裂缝的位置的
releasing them into the air and watching where they eventually collected.
他们把茶叶释放到空气中 并观察其最终聚集的地方 这样才发现了裂缝
Now they did have things like ultrasonic leak detectors and other high-tech hardware on board
现在在国际空间站上 确实有像超声波检漏仪之类的高科技设备
but sometimes you just have to hack together towards a solution.
但有时你只需要拼凑出一个解决方案
Or as some people say MacGyver the heck out of things.
或者说像马盖先的机智那样
And space flight is full of stories like this.
而在太空飞行中充满了这样的故事
Hey, the Martian is great movie, a great book
嘿 火星救援是一部伟大的电影 也是一本伟大的书
where the entire story is pretty much
在那里 整个故事几乎都是
you know Mark Watney hacking together solutions for problems
Mark Watney在拼凑着各种解决方案
using the things that aren't well suited to the task.
用着不是很适合的东西
And lots of disco music as well.
还有很多迪斯科音乐
But anyway I thought this would be a great time to list some of my favorite space hacks from space history
但无论如何 借此机会我来列举一些我最喜欢的太空历史中的太空破解
Starting out with a rare example of a literal life hack.
从一个罕见的生活小技巧开始
如www.youtube.com/c/5MinuteCraftsYouTube 以及微博视频 吐槽那些沙雕小技巧 系列
Youtube is full of dumb life hacks
油管上有很多愚蠢的生活小技巧
but to be honest they are they're mostly useless.
但说实话 大部分这些生活小技巧只是沙雕
But on Apollo 13 the astronauts had to figure out how to put a square peg into a round hole
但在阿波罗13号上 宇航员们必须想出把方桩塞进圆洞里的方法
when the lunar module carbon dioxide scrubbers needed to be replaced
这发生在登月舱上二氧化碳过滤器需要更换的时候
and the square lithium hydroxide canisters from the command module
而指令舱的氢氧化锂过滤罐是方形的
were incompatible allowing them to be the wrong shape, right.
与圆形的形状不匹配
So yeah in flight they had to build an adapter using only the stuff that they had on board the spacecraft
那么没错 在飞行过程中 他们不得不只使用飞船上的东西来制造一个适配器
which was obviously stripped down for its journey to the moon.
很明显是只能使用本应用于登月的物资
They have a plastic bag, a piece of stiff cardboard, a lot of gray tape which we sometimes call duct tape
他们使用一个塑料袋 一块硬纸板 很多灰色的胶带或者胶布
and a space suit ventilation hose.
还有一个宇航服通风软管
youtu.be/pPBKBOuyYPI
And they built this together and I have a video where I actually replicated this.
那么宇航员一起完成了这个适配器 而我也复制了这个过程 并制作了一个视频
The hose went into the suit air system
软管连上宇航服的空气系统
and that would then continue to suck air through the system
这样就会继续通过这个系统来吸气
and keep the astronauts alive for their return to Earth.
并让宇航员活着返回地球
So yeah that was a rare literal life hack.
那么 是的 这是一个罕见的生活小技巧
But it's a perfect example of how you might MacGyver something together to make the mission work.
但这是一个完美的例子来说明你可能需要马盖先的机智来拼凑东西才能完成任务
I mean Apollo 13 is full of many other hacks and improvised solution
我是指阿波罗13号充满了许多其他临时拼凑的解决方案
that they had to you know come up with to basically deal with the problems on hand.
他们不得不用手头的东西来想着法解决问题
You know it's basically you can't get spare parts or tools shipped up.
基本上来讲你不能得到快递送来的备件或者工具
You have to make do with what you have.
你必须用你(目前)所拥有的东西来拼凑
Now as it turns out the Apollo missions are full of critical hacks
那么事实证明 阿波罗任务中充满了关键性的拼凑
that save the day or the mission and sometimes the crew.
这些拼凑 迅速地扭转了局面 或者是拯救了任务以及乘员的生命
Apollo 11 had a moment where the crew discovered a circuit breaker cap on the floor of the lunar module
阿波罗11号曾遇到过这样的情况 乘员们在月球舱的地板上发现了一个断路器的盖子
after they did their surface EVA.
这发生在他们做完月表舱外活动(EVA)后
Buzz thinks that he probably hit it with the backpack of his EVA suit
Buzz认为他可能是用EVA服的背包撞掉了这个盖子
and he broke off the circuit breaker which had been popped out after landing.
或者说就把着陆后弹出的断路器弄断了
Now that might not sound bad.
那么 这可能听起来没那么坏
I mean there was a lot of circuit breakers
我是指 断路器很多
but this one in particular was very much a circuit they needed to unbreak.
但这个被搞断了的断路器是不能出问题的
This one controlled power to the ascent engine
这个断路器控制着上升级发动机的动力
which was needed for leaving the moon and getting back into orbit.
这是离开月球并入轨所需要的
So without being able to close that breaker
那么 如果不能关上那个断路器
they would have had a hard time lighting the engine and returning.
他们将很难开启发动机并返回
But after a bit of thinking Buzz Aldrin figured out how to close the breaker using a pen.
但经过一番思考 Buzz Aldrin想出了用笔来关闭断路器的方法
To be clear this wasn't the famous fisher space pen
要说明的是 这不是著名的渔夫太空笔
because those have metal cases and jamming bits of metal into electrical panels is not a good idea.
因为那可是金属外壳的笔 而把金属碎片塞进带电的仪表里可不是什么好主意
It was a more mundane plastic felt pen which saved the day
拯救任务的是一支比较普通的塑料毡笔
and actually remember seeing this
而其实我还记得
was on display along with the broken circuit breaker at the Museum of Flight.
我是在飞行博物馆看到的这支笔 当时正和破损的断路器一起展出
So Apollo 17 is another great example.
那么阿波罗17号是另一个很好的例子
The lunar rover it required and improvised repair
它的月球车需要临时修理
Gene Cernan managed to drop a hammer on one of the fenders
Gene Cernan用锤子砸掉了挡泥板
which were essential to stop lunar dust getting kicked up by the wheels.
而挡泥板可以阻止月球尘埃被轮子卷起
So when these while they're still on EVA
那么当他们还在EVA的时候
they attempt to tape the broken part back on using their duct tape.
就试图用胶带把破损的部分粘回去
And that sort of worked but it fell off quickly
某种程度上也算是起了作用 但它很快就掉了下来
because the moon dust essentially ruined the tape's adhesion.
因为月球尘埃根本上破坏了胶带的粘性
By the end of the first day's EVA, there was completely covered in moon dust.
第一天的EVA结束时 胶带完全被月球尘埃覆盖
So while the crew slept on the surface of the moon.
那么当乘员们在月球表面睡觉时
Engineers and astronauts back on Earth tried to come up with a better solution.
地球上的工程师和宇航员们试图想出一个更好的解决方案
So their version of the repair, they took four of the lunar maps which were on cardboard
那么他们的修复方案是 他们把四张纸板上的月球地图拿出来
and they taped them together using the tape on the lunar module
并用月球舱上的胶带把它们粘在一起
where there was less dust to ruin the adhesion.
而月球舱里的灰尘较少 不会破坏胶带的黏性
And then when they went out to the rover
然后当他们走到漫游车上的时候
they fixed it onto the rover using clamps that were borrowed from the optical alignment telescope.
他们用光学校准望远镜上的夹子 把它固定在漫游车上
So this solution lasted for the rest of the surface stay
那么这个方案就一直持续到宇航员离开月球表面
and in the end actually they they needed the clamps back and so they took the maps back with them
最后其实他们是需要夹子的 所以也把地图带回去了
and those also are on display in the National Air and Space museum.
而这些也在美国国家航空航天博物馆展出
Still taped together nearly five decades later.
近五十年后 还粘在一起
Not all the Apollo hacks were physical.
并不是所有的阿波罗计划中的拼凑都涉及到实物
Of course I love to talk about Apollo 14 which had a broken abort switch
当然 我这里要说的是阿波罗14号的中止开关坏了
which would make it impossible for them to land on the moon.
而这将使他们不能着陆月球
But computer programmer Don Eyles who is in mission control came up with a solution
但在任务控制室的计算机程序员Don Eyles想出了一个解决办法
which involved editing the computer memory of the Apollo guidance computer.
其中包括编辑阿波罗导航计算机的计算机内存
They basically convinced the computer that it was already in an abort mode
基本上就是让计算机相信自己已经处在中止模式了
原理是计算机的中断
and stopping it from triggering another abort mode.
这样就会阻止它触发另一个中止模式
Meanwhile the computer was actually landing on the moon.
与此同时 计算机实际上已经登陆月球了
And I like to think of this as the world's greatest tech support call.
我认为这是世界上最强的技术支持电话
So as Apollo wound down the last flight of Saturn V would launch the Skylab into orbit
那么当阿波罗号结束最后一次飞行时 土星五号将把天空实验室送入轨道
中文文章版详见 @超超级loveovergold 比肩阿波罗13号抢险——拯救天空实验室行动纪实
weibo.com/ttarticle/p/show?id=2309404493356171395222，weibo.com/ttarticle/p/show?id=2309404493668676403221
and that didn't go according to plan.
而这并没有按计划进行
About a minute into the flight as the vehicle started to go supersonic
在飞行一分钟后 当火箭开始进入超音速状态的时候
the shock wave tore off a section of the meteorite shielding
冲击波撕开了一段陨石防护罩
and later during stage separation, a retro rocket blasted upwards
而后在器箭分离时 一枚反推火箭向上点火
and it tore off one of the solar panels.
并将其中一块太阳能电池板撕下
The other solar panel was found to be held in place
另一块太阳能电池板被发现固定在原地
because it was tangled in debris from the meteoroid shielding.
因为它被陨石防护罩的碎片缠住了
The meteoroid shielding was also part of the thermal control system
陨石防护罩也是热控系统的一部分
so temperatures in the station quickly rose to uninhabitable levels
因此 空间站的温度很快就上升到不适合居住的程度
and without all the solar panels, this station didn't have enough power to operate at full power.
而太阳能电池板出现缺损 使得空间站没有足够的电力来全功率运行
天空实验室2任务是使用土星1B火箭发射阿波罗飞船与天空实验室对接的载人飞船任务
So the crew of Skylab 2 were expected to launch the next day
所以 原本计划在第二天发射的天空实验室2任务
but they gave them like an extra 10 days to figure out how to fix all these problems.
并没有进行 而是给了其乘员额外10天时间来考虑解决问题的方案
Since everyone back is trying to work on solutions to this.
因为那时每个人都在想办法解决这些问题
You've got the backup crew figuring out EVAs and trying to design stuff.
比如备用乘员组在研究EVA 并试图设计一些东西
In the end in that short amount of time they built a space parasol
最后 在这么短的时间里 他们造出了一个太空伞
which they would extend through one of the experimental air locks and pop open
这将通过一个实验性的气闸延伸并弹开
and then pull against the side of the station
并且靠着空间站的一侧来拉动
and that got the thermal situation under control.
而这让温度过高的情况得到了控制
The solar panel that was locked in place.
而对于被锁定的太阳能面板
Well they performed a fascinating unorthodox EVA
他们进行了一次精彩而非常规的EVA
where the Apollo spacecraft moved into within a few meters of the station.
也就是 阿波罗飞船进入到空间站的几米范围之内
While astronaut Paul Weitz leaned out of the hatch
当宇航员Paul Weitz从舱门里探身出来的时候
using a 10 foot long pole with a hook on the end to try and pull the debris clear of the spring-loaded panel.
用一根3米长 末端带有钩子的杆子 试着把碎片从带有弹簧的面板上拉开
You're like someone on a boat.
这就像船上的人一样
It was literally a boat tool they were using.
实际上他们用的就是船用工具
P. Carr of course had to manually fly the Apollo to stop them colliding.
(与此同时) P. Carr当然得手动驾驶阿波罗飞船来阻止它们相撞
Every time they pulled the spacecraft, they would get pulled together.
每次他们拉动空间站的时候 (阿波罗飞船和空间站)就被拉到一起
Ultimately this didn't work because the strap had rivets that had embedded themselves in the structure.
最终这样做并没有成功 因为(碎片)带子上的铆钉已经嵌入到结构当中
So instead the panels were freed by cutting the strap
所以只好把带子切开 把面板释放出来
and they put the cutters on the end of a 25-foot pole and they operated them remotely.
他们把切割器放在7.6米长的杆子上 然后远程操作
Initially this didn't seem to be working so P. Carr have trying to cut them.
起初 这似乎并没起作用 那么P. Carr就尝试去切割它们
He made his way up the pole
他沿着杆子往上走
and at that moment the strap snapped at the pole what pulled away from the station
而在那一刻 在拉开空间站的杆子上 带子断裂了
knocking P. off into space
这把P. Carr撞到太空中
but of course fortunately he was tethered to the station.
当然 幸运的是 他被拴在了空间站上
But that was a hairy moment.
但那是一个惊悚的时刻
So there was a whole lot more in the story of Skylab.
类似的事情在天空实验室中还发生过很多次
The whole rescue and repair is full of procedures like this.
整个救援和维修过程都充满了这样的步骤
And equally I've got to say on the Soviet side Salute 7 had a lot of improvisations in MacGyvering.
而同样我得说在苏联方面的礼炮7号也有很多马盖先式的临场发挥
It was a pretty dramatic rescue not quite as dramatic as the recent movie by the way.
没错 这是一次很有戏剧性的救援 尽管没有最近的电影那么充满戏剧性
Anyway the shuttle era they had a few moments.
总之在航天飞机时代 也有过类似的情况
In 1998 there was a case where they had a smoke alarm that was going off all the time
在1998年的时候 遇到了烟雾警报器一直在响的情况
and they patched that up with grey tape.
于是乘员用灰色胶带把它补上了
But my favorite one is on STS-51-D in 1985.
但我最喜欢的是1985年的STS-51-D任务
They were performing a satellite launch and the satellite went wrong.
这次任务在进行卫星发射时 卫星出了问题
After it launched there was a release.
在卫星发射后 有一个释放装置(出了问题)
The release mechanism was supposed to flip a physical lever on the satellite that would arm it.
释放装置的机制 应该是打开卫星上的一个实体控制杆来解除卫星的固定
And they had to figure out how to fix it.
而他们必须想办法来修复它
Now one plan was to put an astronaut out on the end of the arm
那么其中一个计划是把一个宇航员放在臂的末端
and have him sort of reach up and flip the switch.
并让他伸手来打开开关
But they thought this was going to be too dangerous because satellite was spinning.
但他们认为这样做太危险了 因为卫星在旋转
Instead they built a tool in the cabin using stuff they had on hand.
相反 他们用手边的东西在船舱里做了一个工具
They called this the fly swatter
他们把这个叫做苍蝇拍
and they built it out of like window shades gray tape.
这是用窗帘和灰胶带做出来的
And then they had to perform an EVA to put this on the end of the robot arm.
然后他们必须进行一次EVA 把这个东西放在机械臂的末端
And there was no EVA scheduled so they had to totally improvise how to do this.
当时没有计划中的EVA 所以他们不得不完全临场发挥
So they did this and then re-rendezvoused with the spacecraft, flipped the switch with the new tools
那么先固定了苍蝇拍 然后和卫星重新交会 再用新工具打开开关
and it still didn't work.
但还是没能成功
So in the end they left the spacecraft in space and came back on the next mission or a later mission.
所以最后他们把卫星留在了太空 然后在下一次或以后的任务中再回来解决问题
And they had to install like a bypass box on the lockout system
而他们不得不在锁定系统上安装了一个旁路盒(来解决问题)
so that they could send the spacecraft to geostationary orbit.
这样他们就可以将航天器送入地球静止轨道 也就是目标轨道
And of course it's still there today.
当然 今天它还在那里
根据维基百科，在90年代退役 en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syncom#Syncom_IV_(Leasat)
I'm not sure whether it's still operational today but certainly operated for a fair amount of time.
我不知道现在它是否还在运行 但肯定运行了相当长的时间
Moving on to the space station era.
话题来到国际空间站时代
You would imagine that having regular deliveries from the Earth
你可以想象 从地球上定期运送东西
would mean that you no longer have the need to Macgyver tools.
将意味着 你不再需要马盖先式的临场发挥的方法
Hey they have a 3d printer there you think that would solve all their problems.
嘿 国际空间站有台3D打印机 怎么着都能解决问题吧
But no they are still hacking together things on board to solve problems they didn't anticipate.
但并没有 他们仍然在临时拼凑着空间站上的东西来解决各种各样的意外
While the station was under construction
当空间站仍在建设的时候
one of the solar panel pairs were launched early on and mounted on top of the station in a temporary location.
其中一对太阳能板在早些时候发射入轨 并安装在空间站顶部的一个临时位置
After the truss was finished those panels were then restored
在空间站桁架完成搭建后 这些面板被恢复到正确的位置
and the unit was relocated to the end of the truss where they would be redeployed
也就是把太阳能板的位置移动到桁架末端 并重新部署(展开)
but as the panels were extending out something snagged and the panels tore so they stopped the deployment.
但当面板延伸出来的时候 有东西卡住了 而面板撕裂了 所以他们停止了部署
And they had to figure out how to fix this.
他们必须想办法来解决这个问题
What they came up with was a set of giant cufflinks
他们想出的办法是使用一套巨大的袖扣
and these were fabricated from wires and other materials they had on board.
而这些都是用空间站上的电线和其他材料制作的
So the panels are right out at the furthest point on the station
那么这些板子处在空间站上的最远端
and to reach this location they actually had to extend the station's manipulator arm
而要到达这个位置 他们实际上必须延长空间站的机械臂
using a tool that was carried by the space shuttle to inspect the heat shield.
并使用航天飞机上携带的工具来检查隔热罩
Because the robot arm on the shuttle
(同样地) 因为航天飞机上的机械臂
had to be able to reach under and see the heat shield so it had an extension.
得能够到达下面并看到隔热罩 所以得延长它
So the astronaut rode the end of this thing out to the site
那么宇航员就得骑着这个东西的末端到空间站的外部
and then carefully threaded their cufflinks through the panel
之后小心翼翼地将袖扣穿过面板
adding extra support where it was tearing.
并在撕裂的地方增加额外的支撑力
And I say this carefully
我之所以说这得小心翼翼
because of course there's a lot of electrical power flowing through these panels
是因为会有很多电力流经这些面板
and the panels themselves are very delicate
以及面板本身是非常脆弱的
and either damaging the panels or the astronaut would be a very bad outcome.
而无论是损伤到面板还是宇航员 都会非常糟糕
Afterwards the panels were extended and they still operate today with the emergency fix still in place.
之后 太阳能板得到了展开 而且至今仍在运行 而这样的应急修复措施依然存在
Another improvised fix for the ISS solar power system was Sunita Williams and Akihiko Hoshide.
而另一次临时修复了国际空间站太阳能系统的宇航员是苏妮塔·威廉斯和星出彰彦
They were replacing a main bus switching unit
在他们更换一个主总线开关装置的时候
and they found themselves unable to bolt the thing back together with the tools they had on hand
发现用手头的东西无法将其重新组装起来
due to the bolts being stuck.
这是因为螺栓被卡住了
So they analyzed the problem.
于是他们分析了问题所在
They figured out there was debris and metal shavings getting stuck in there.
他们发现有碎片和金属屑卡在里面了
So they developed some tools again on orbit.
所以他们又在轨道上开发了一些工具
They took a jumper cable they had and cut it, splayed out the wires and made themselves a wire brush.
他们将一条跳线剪断并铺开 就这样自制了一把钢丝刷
They modified a toothbrush for EVA use
并把这样的牙刷进行了EVA作业化改造
which means you know extra big handles and lanyards and hoops to hang it on.
这意味着 会使用额外的大手柄 挂绳还有环来挂着它
And so yeah with those custom tools in hand they went out performed another EVA
那么是的 带着这些定制的工具 他们就去执行另一个EVA的任务了
and they completed the installation
之后他们完成了安装
returning the 200 billion dollar station to full power with the help of a two dollar toothbrush.
于是在价值两刀牙刷的帮助下 将价值2000亿刀的空间站恢复到满功率运行
The more you look at problem solving in space
越研究太空中的问题解决方案
the more you you discover stories and moments like this,
越会发现这样的故事和时刻
where you're far from home and you have to work with what you have on hand
这会发生在那样远离家乡 而必须用手头的东西来工作的地方
but at least the crew are backed up by teams of experts on the ground
但至少空间站乘员有地面专家团队来支持他们的工作
who can help check that your crazy plan will actually work.
这样的专家团队可以帮忙检查你的疯狂计划并让其实际起作用
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]